你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到pwn学院
welcome to pwn College
我是Yan，今天要讨论的是
I'm Yan and today we're going to be talking about
程序误用的保护机制
program misuse mitigations
我们已经简单探讨了程序误用
so we've dug into how programs are misused at a very high level
我们会在习题中深入研究
in this module and we're going to dig into that with the practice problems
甚至在习题中
and even in the practice problems
你会发现在某些情况
you will find certain cases
感觉开发者在与你对抗
where it feels like the developers are fighting against you
防止你误用程序
to keep you from misusing the software
这当然是有意为之
and that's of course intentional
一般来说，随着开发人员
in general as developers identify
发现越来越多的软件安全问题
more and more and more security issues with software
这些安全问题形成了一些相同主题
and when those security issues start coalescing into common themes
保护机制就会被开发出来，以减少
mitigations are developed to try to reduce the harm
特定安全缺陷类型的伤害
from a given security flaw
我们已经在黑客团队的攻击中看到了这一点
we already saw this in action in the Hacking Team hack
我们在最初的课程介绍中讨论的
that we discussed in the very very introduction to the course
你们会在接下来的课程中不断看到保护机制
and you'll see this constantly throughout the rest of the class
我们会讨论一类安全漏洞
we'll talk about a class of security flaw
再讨论大量保护措施
and we'll talk about numerous mitigations
它们被创造出来是为了
that have been created to try to
一般是减少伤害，而不是消除伤害
generally reduce harm but not eliminate harm
不是因为我们不想消除伤害
not because we don't want to eliminate harm
而是因为这非常困难
but because it's actually extremely difficult to do so
所以只能尽力减小某类安全缺陷的影响
but try to reduce the impact of certain security flaws
好吧
all right
我们先讨论一个具体的保护机制
let's talk specifically about a mitigation that
你会在这个模块中遇到它
you will run into in the course of this module
这个保护机制是（防止）
and that mitigation is
由于对参数的疏忽大意引起的命令注入
command injection through basically uncareful handling of some programs of their arguments
很多时候，作为攻击者的你，能够
right so often times you are able to as an attacker
将命令注入到软件
inject the command into software
就如同你在本模块某些习题中做的那样
as you do in some of the levels of this module
使它执行你输入的命令
and have it execute commands on your behalf
这种情况经常发生，这很令人沮丧
this happens depressingly frequently
8年前
as of 8 years ago
这是十大最常见的安全漏洞之一
this was one of the top 10 most common security vulnerabilities
位列OWASP榜单前十
the owasp top 10
现在它在OWASP榜单前25，命令注入
now it is still in the owasp top 25 command injection
所以这仍然是一个常见的漏洞
so it's still a common vulnerability
在利用此漏洞进行攻击的过程中
in the course of carrying out an attack utilizing this vulnerability
攻击者通常会使用/bin/sh执行命令
attackers will often cause commands to be executed with /bin/sh
当你使用/bin/sh执行某些命令时
when you execute something with /bin/sh
假设
let's say
一般情况，没保护机制时
normally premitigation
你在执行命令时
you'd be executing them
能直接使用你所劫持进程的权限
with whatever privileges the program that you're hijacking had
这就聊到这个表情包了
and that's where this meme comes in
显然这两种情况都不好
obviously it's bad in both cases
程序以root身份运行
in whether the program was running as root
或不是以root身份运行
or it wasn't running as root
但如果程序以root身份运行，那会特别特别不好
but it's very very very bad if the program is running as root
程序以root身份运行的，且你能劫持它
the program runs as root and you can hijack it to
能利用它对输入的错误处理方式，来注入命令
or do a command injection in some mishandling of input by this program
这能让你以root身份执行命令
that causes you to be able to run commands as root
这显然是对系统安全性的巨大摧残
that's obviously brutalizing to security of the system
因此保护机制应运而生
and so mitigation was created
基本现代的命令解释器或者说shell，都有实现
that basically for modern implementations of command interpreters or shells
如果运行的shell有setuid位
if the shell is running as setuid
如果它的euid
so if it's effective user ID
这个我们上节课讨论过
as we discussed in the previous lecture
是root，但实际uid不是root
is root but its real user ID is not root
算是一种暂时性的root身份
kind of temporarily root
它会降回实际uid的权限
it will actually drop privileges back down to the real user ID
这是出于安全考虑
for safety reasons
因为这几乎总是
because almost always let's say or very frequently
代表有被命令注入
this was a sign of a command injection being exploited
以实现权限提升
to achieve privilege escalation on a machine
当然
of course
有时候你是故意这么做的
sometimes you do this intentionally
你有个带setuid位的程序要用system
you have a setuid program that use a system
libc中的system函数
the system libc function
执行一些shell命令
to execute some shell command
你不希望降低权限
you don't want the shell dropping privileges
你得重写一下
you would have to rewrite that
写成/bin/sh -p
to execute /bin/sh -p
而不是/bin/sh
instead of /bin/sh
-p是一个可以传递给shell的参数
-p is a flag that you can pass to the shell
这样它就不会降低权限
so that it won't drop privileges
当然，要传递这个参数
but of course passing that flag requires
需要有比寻常命令注入能获得的，更大的控制力
some more control than your average command injection actually gets you
因为在寻常的命令注入中
because in your average command injection
你运行这个命令时
by the time that you are running in that command
由于这个保护机制，你已经不是root了
you are no longer root because of this mitigation
所以
right so
如果你在这个模块中
if you are in the course of this module
要执行/bin/sh或/bin/bash
trying to execute /bin/sh or /bin/bash
记得传入-p参数
make sure to pass it the -p flag
不管怎样
anyways
这个是程序误用保护机制的一个例子
the shell is one example of kind of program misuse mitigation
我会再介绍一个更通用的例子
I'm going to give you a more general example
然后介绍一下后续相关技术
before casting a wide eye toward the future
更通用的例子是Wireshark
the slightly more general example is Wireshark
Wireshark是一个非常流行的网络嗅探工具
Wireshark is a network sniffer very popular one
这是一款很棒的软件
it's a great piece of software
曾经
historically
它一直是一些安全问题的主题
it's been a subject of some security problems
为什么
why
因为Wireshark需要大量访问权限
because Wireshark needs a lot of access
它需要能够嗅探网络流量
it needs to be able to sniff network traffic
这不是随便一个进程就能做到的
that is not something that any old process can do
所以通常人们以root权限运行Wireshark
so typically people run Wireshark as root
2 Wireshark不仅会捕获流量，还会解析流量
two Wireshark tries to parse traffic as well as just capture it
它能很好地分析流量
and it provides a lot of very good analysis of this traffic
能解析非常非常多的不同协议
of many many many different protocols like
巨多的协议
very many protocols
所有这些协议解析器都可能存在安全问题
all these protocol parsers can have security problems in themselves right
为了防止因安全问题导致
and as a mitigation to prevent security problems leading to
攻击者在受害机器上以root身份运行代码
attackers running code as root on the victim machine
为了缓解这种情况，Wireshark开发人员将其分成了两个程序
as a mitigation here the Wireshark developers put into two programs
一个记录流量，一个分析流量
one that records traffic and one that analyzes it
实际上不止两个
actually more than two but
我们把它化简一下
you know we just simplify it
这是另一种专门的保护机制
so that's another kind of ad hoc mitigation
如同/bin/sh的那个，增加保护机制以对抗特定类型的问题
like the /bin/sh one that was deployed to fight certain classes of problems
我会提一下一个通用的保护机制
and I'll mention a general mitigation
我们会在后面的模块中深入学习它
and we'll actually study it much more in depth a couple modules from now
更通用的解决方案是使用沙盒
but a more general mitigation to program is use the sandboxing
你拿到这个程序
so you take the program
你把它隔离开
and you actually wall it off
使其远离敏感数据
from anything sensitive
远离它正常执行用不到的
or from anything it doesn't need to have access to in its normal execution
尽力确保
and you try to make sure that
即使程序被误用了
even if the program is misused somehow
也能将伤害降到最低
harm is minimized
我们将在后面的沙盒模块中探索这个概念
we'll explore this concept a lot several modules later in the sandboxing module
好了，这就是安全保护机制
all right so that was security mitigations
希望这能为未来打下基础
hope that kind of set the stage for the future of the course
我们几乎会在每个模块中讨论保护机制
we'll talk about like I said mitigations in almost every module
因为几乎所有的安全问题
because almost all of these security problems
已经被考虑
have been thought of for
且可能与之对抗了几十年
and fought for sometimes for decades
好吧
all right
祝你好运
good luck